The Right To Resist

Keith Laumer

Worlds of IF – June 1971

First, can you keep from losing?

Then, can you keep from winning?

THE crash of breaking glass was like an explosion in the darkness. Planetary Administrator Andrew Galt came awake, rolled off the side of the bed and hugged the floor. In the silence a final glass fragment fell from the window frame to the rug. Galt got to his feet, saw the paper-wrapped bolt lying by the dresser.

END TYRANNY ON COLMAR

was lettered neatly in red on the back of a recently published ration application form. Galt grunted and tossed the paper away. It was nearly dawn, he saw. He dressed and went down to the kitchen. Freddy, his butler-valet-driver-bodyguard-secretary was there, brewing coffee.

“You’re up early, Mr. Administrator,” he said formally. “No protocol this early in the day, Freddy!’ Galt said as he sat down at the table. “A few of my admirers came by to give me a nice sendoff for the day. Colmar’s twentieth anniversary of independence!’ Galt gave a snort that was not quite the laugh he had intended.

“Don’t take it so hard, Andy,” Freddy said. He poured coffee, put a cup before Galt, sat down opposite him. “You’ve always done what was best in a tough situation.”

Galt looked at him sardonically as he sipped the bitter brew. “Funny how you assume it wasn’t flowers they threw, Freddy. Anybody would think I wasn’t popular.”

Freddy lifted his powerful shoulders. “You can’t please ‘em all,” he said.

“It seems I’m not pleasing any of them.”

“You’re doing what you’ve got to do, Andy. The Colony’s a marginal operation. It’s not your fault that times are tough. These babies want it all now, that’s all. They see too much Interplan trideo, they’ve got ideas about how life ought to be fat and soft. They’ve got to face up to facts sometime. Colmar’s a poor world. We just can’t afford a three-hour day and welfare caviar.”

“Try telling that to some Econ graduate doing his time in the labor pool.”

“I know; so they gripe. What about it? If they’d been here back in the old days they’d have had something to gripe about. Do they ever think about what the first people here had to face up to, seventy years ago?”

“Of course not,” Galt said. “Why should they? These aren’t the old days. This is now. And they’re young. They want to live today, not some time in the next century. I can’t blame ‘em.”

“Sure—and so did your grandad want to live—and mine. That’s why they came out here—to nothing. To make something of it—of a dead world—something that hadn’t existed before. They had no guarantees, no route back. They had to whip Colmar or die—and plenty of them died.”

“Ancient history, Freddy. Today they know there’s something better than hard work and rationing. They want it. And Freddy, so do I—”

“But you’re not whining for it—and one day it’ll happen—you’re working for it like they did back then. It must have been a frightening thing, Andy, when they unloaded from the freighters and looked around and saw a dead world, not even a blade of grass. In seventy years we’ve turned it into a place where a man can live—but not without effort. Let ‘em gripe, Andy—just so they put in their time like everybody else—like you did.”

“Involuntary servitude. Tyranny’ is what they call it.”

Freddy snorted.

“So? What are you supposed to do, back down because they call you dirty names? You know what’s got to be done, Andy. You’re doing it. It takes guts. You got ‘em. More coffee?”

“No, thanks. I might as well go on down to the office. Maybe we’ll beat the rock-throwers for a change.”

“If it was me,” Freddy said in the car, “I’d stay home and to hell with ‘em. Let ‘em see how things go after a few days with nobody making the decisions. They’re complaining now: let ‘em see how it’d be if you. weren’t on the job to untangle the knots—”

“Don’t get carried away, Freddy. Any competent administrative type could do the same job.”

“Maybe,” Freddy said. “It’s not seeing what you have to do that’s tough; it’s doing it when the mob is yelling for your head. You could be the most popular man on Colmar tomorrow if you’d give in.”

“And we’d be bankrupt the day after. Sure, Freddy. But those are just facts; they don’t have any appeal to the emotions.”

-

A FEW early pickets gaped as the administrator’s car swung in through the open gates. In his office, Galt attacked a stack of priority applications: fifty tons of fabricated steel sections for Shaft # 209 versus sixty tons of the same urgently needed for the extension to the loading docks; four loads of feeder fuel in stock to be allocated among nine agencies, all yelling for immediate action; computer components on order for six months by Supply, demanded by Routing to prevent imminent shutdown of the entire NW range …

Galt looked up at a sharp rap at the door. Timmins, the executive officer, poked his head in. Through the open door Galt could hear sounds of an altercation.

“Another delegation to see you,” Timmins said. Galt rose and went out into the corridor. From below came voices raised in anger, other voices replying. Feet clattered on the stairs. A disheveled young man in maintenance grays appeared, Freddy close behind him.

“Hold it, Freddy,” Galt said. Both men stopped. “Let him come up.”

“Chief, he might be armed—” Timmins said quickly, but Galt brushed that aside.

“You want to see me?” he asked the intruder.

“That’s right,” the man in gray said defiantly. He brushed back his hair, straightened his jacket. “We’re citizens; we’ve got a right to be heard.” “Who’s ‘we?’”

“The Party.” The young man said it flatly, as if inviting challenge.

“Come along to the office,” Galt said.

“Frisk them first,” he heard Timmins say as he turned away.

There were five people in the delegation, three men, two women, ranging in age from eighteen to thirty-five, Galt estimated. He knew them all by sight, two by name—not a difficult feat in a population of thirty thousand. One of the women—a plump, pretty girl in nurse’s green—stepped forward and offered Galt a folded paper. Timmins. read it over his shoulder.

“The same old refrain,” the exec said. “Improved public transport, more entertainment facilities, shorter hours. It’s nonsense—”

“It’s not nonsense to us,” the girl said sharply.

“Or to me either, Miss Dolph,” Galt said. “I’d like to lead an easier life myself. Unfortunately, we can’t afford it—not yet.”

“You’ve got yours,” the man in gray said. “Official mansion, official car, the best of everything—”

“Look here,” Timmins started, but Galt waved a hand to silence him.

“Let’s keep it factual—Jonas, isn’t it? My official residence is a standard Class Vb unit; I get the same food, clothing, and power ration as anyone else. As you know. As for the car, I used to walk—until the rock density got a bit high.”

“If you were doing your job the way you ought to, nobody would be throwing things,” Jonas snapped.

“I’ve got an idea Freddy was at the point of bruising you a bit when I happened along. Does that mean you had it coming to you?”

“He’s a hired goon—that’s different.”

“What is it you expect me to do, Jonas, Miss Dolph?”

“Ease the restrictions on life,” the girl said promptly. “Let people enjoy living while they can. Shorten the work day, give us some leisure time activities and facilities, end rationing, increase consumer imports.”

-

GALT nodded. “Anything else?”

“Plenty more,.” Jonas said. “End the labor draft. Raise pay, right across the board. Lift the off-world travel restrictions, bring in more outsystem entertainers.”

“For what it cost to open this new Sector,” another of the delegation spoke up, a small, timid-looking man with a bad complexion, “we could have founded a program of concert artists that would have given us some contact with the cultural life of the Arm.”

“Sector Nineteen gives us a marine agricultural facility,” Galt said mildly. “In twenty years it may be our biggest food producer. We may be able to shorten the time to self-support capability by three decades—”

“We know all the propaganda lines,” Jonas said. “We’ve heard all that before.”

“Then what are you doing here?” Galt snapped.

That’s easy, Mr. Administrator,” Jonas said with a sneer. “We don’t believe the official line.”

“The records are open to the public,” Galt said.

“They can be faked, too.”

“Why?” Galt shot back.

“To delude the public.”

“Why should I want to delude the public?”

“For obvious reasons—”

“Name them,” Galt snapped.

“All right. To justify your program of overwork and underpay, long hours and no recreation, luxury for the few at the cost of slavery for the many—”’

“What luxury?” Galt cut in sharply. “We’ve already covered that particular allegation. It’s nonsense and you know it—and so does everybody in this room.”

“Look, chief, this has gone far enough,” Willis started, but Galt cut him off.

“You’re here charging me and the rest of the administration with a deep, dark plot—”

“You’re depriving the people of their basic rights,” Jonas shouted.

“You name one right you’re being deprived of, Jonas, and I’ll personally see that you get a lifetime pension,” Galt said.

“All right—the right to a reasonable amount of leisure time, for openers. The eight-hour day went out with coal-fired ground cars.”

“What would you call a reasonable amount of leisure time?”

“Time enough to do a few things. To have hobbies, play a musical instrument, visit your ^friends—”

“Wrong, Mr. Jonas. That’s nice, maybe, but it’s not reasonable. Reasonable means what’s physically possible. We have just so much manpower,” he went on, raising his voice as Jonas tried to cut in. “We have to allocate that manpower in such a way as to keep industrial operations going at the rate required to produce enough exportable output to keep the economy afloat. You want more imported trideos and traveling art shows? Fine. Then we’ll have to work longer hours, not shorter.”

“Official bullwash,” Jonas spat out the words like a bite of wormy apple.

“As I said, the records are public. Look at them or not, suit yourself. But don’t come bursting in here again with your proposals for instant Utopia until you’ve done your homework.”

“That’s what I thought we’d get,” one of the women said in a shrill, nervous voice. “A brush-off. Excuses. We should have known better than to waste our time.” She glared at Galt with eyes as sharp as stakes.

“I welcome constructive suggestions,” Galt said, meeting her gaze steadily. “Come back when you have one.”

“We won’t be back,” Jonas said. “We’re through talking.” They departed, slamming doors.

-

“REMIND you of anything?”

Galt asked Timmins when silence had fallen again.

“Painfully. Except that there were only fifty of us—”

“Forty-two,” Galt corrected.

“—and this time half the population is agitating. No one tried to explain to us; if they had, we might even have listened.”

“Don’t count on it. We wanted change—any change. We got it.”

“And all the grief that went with it. But these people today won’t listen. They remember when we threw BuCol out; Pinchot and a few others were promising them the world. Twenty years later they’re still on short rations. They’re unhappy. And they mean business, Andy. This isn’t just a little band of soreheads—”

“I know all that, Ben. Are you suggesting I should promise them pie in the sky? What happens when they discover it isn’t there?”

Timmons looked solemn. “Andy, for this generation—and for a lot of people who ought to know better—you symbolize everything that’s wrong with life. By removing you, you see, they can remove their problems—they think.”

“You’re suggesting I quit while I’m ahead?”

“I’m suggesting you quit while you’re alive, damn it!”

“And do what? Sit back and watch Colmar die?”

“You’ve had offers—three in the last six months that I know of; I wrote the answers turning them down. You could still take that post at Yale, lecturing on problems of the frontier economy—”

“And read in the fax about how the Colmar experiment failed. Ben, have you ever considered what would happen if we had to throw in the towel and invite BuCol back in? They’d close the colony down, evacuate us to Terra—to beehive housing, synthetic rations—”

“I know. It’s unthinkable. And dammit, Colmar can make it! We have the minerals, the seas—a whole world to exploit!” Timmins smacked his fist into his palm. “If they could just see it! Just give us time!”

“Bringing life to a dead world is a big undertaking, Ben. Maybe too big. Maybe we haven’t got what it takes. But I have to stay and do what I can—for as long as I can.”

“And be a martyr,” Timmins said grimly.

“There’s nothing noble about it,” Galt said. “This is my home-world. I couldn’t survive on Terra either. I’m fighting for my life; the only life I know.”

“Then don’t throw it away. Let me recruit an escort for you. I can get a dozen TSA regulars detailed from Aldo—”

“Negative, Ben. Importing foreign gun-handlers to protect me from the people that voted me in would be the end.”

“Then what in God’s name are you going to do?”

“Play it by ear—and hope Sector Nineteen starts paying off in time.”

“Comes up with a miracle, you mean.”

“I’d accept a miracle right now,” Galt said wearily, “if it could be arranged.”

-

TWO weeks later Timmins laid a paper on Galt’s desk. It had been a time of rising tensions and near-riots, broken glass—and at least one assassination attempt which had put Freddy in the hospital with third-degree laser burns.

“Weinberg, out at Thirteen,” Timmins said. “I thought you ought to see it.” The executive officer’s face was haggard with lost sleep.

Galt scanned the paper. “Livestock? Chickens? What the devil’s he doing out there, starting a zoo?”

“Experimental animals,” Timmins pointed out. “He wants to run some kind of tests on them.”

Galt rubbed his eyes. “He knows we’re on the shortest meat ration since Colonization,” he said wearily. “I’m surprised at Weinberg. Tell him no. Remind him he’s out there to supplement our protein supply, not deplete it. And ask him what he’s doing about the slimemould contamination problem he’s been reporting on.”

Timmins nodded and turned to go. Galt stopped him before he reached the door.

“Wait a minute, Ben. Disregard that last outburst. I’m too damn tired to think straight. If Dick Weinberg thinks he needs a flock of goats, damn it, he probably needs a flock of goats. Set it up—triple—A priority.”

Timmins nodded again, more brightly.

“And tell them to save a seat on the flier for me,” Galt added. “I’m going out and see what he’s up to.”

Timmins frowned. “That might not be a good idea, Andy. There was rioting at the port this afternoon and—”

“Set it up,” Galt snapped, then grimaced. “I’m sorry, Ben. Nerves. Just get me on the flier. I’ll ride out under a stack of old burlap bags if you say so.”

“I’ll set it up,” Timmins said tonelessly.

-

THE view from the cargo flier was a monotonous vista of eroded ridges, gullied plains, of rock, gravel and sand, stretching across the endless miles. After the narrow green belt of the capital had been passed—and its surrounding five-mile farm strip—forty miles of undeveloped desert intervened before the dull green of a bioadapted valley appeared, far off to the west. Another seventy-five miles of arid, lifeless badlands unrolled beneath the flier; then ahead the curve of the coast and the black-blue sea beyond. They were within five miles of the Experimental Station before Galt could make out the fragile tracings of irrigation ditches, the patterns of agri-formed fields, the vivid green specs that were transplanted trees shading a straggle of buildings. Offshore of the station, Galt noted, the lifeless sea was stained a dark umber. The flier landed on the scraped rectangle behind the sprawling, aluminum-and-white station. A chill wind blew sand across the open ground to ping against the flier’s sides with a restless whispering.

Weinberg was there to meet Galt, a sturdily built, red-haired man with big solemn eyes and a wide, downcurving mouth that belied his brisk optimism of manner.

“Glad to see you, Mr. Administrator—you bring my goats and birds and stuff?” he said, pumping Galt’s hand. “Come on out of this damned wind.”

The marine ecologist’s office, laboratory and living quarters comprised a single large untidy room with stone countertops, a clutter of glassware, a desk heaped with papers, a cot, a table with a hot-plate and dirty dishes.

“Here, sit down, Andy, how about a cup of coffee and a slice of cake?”

“Dick, what’s this about animal experiments? I understand we’re going to add seafood to our diet—”

“Sure, sure, I’ll tell you all about it. How’re things in the city? I hear they’re giving you a hard time, throwing rocks, the works.”

“Things aren’t good. Ben Timmins says all we need is a small miracle from you to solve everything. You don’t happen to have one in stock, do you?”

“A small miracle, the man says,” Weinberg said cheerfully, rattling cups. He poured, dumped things on a tray, brought it over. Galt took the cup and sipped, accepted the small plate with the slice of yellow-brown cake.

“Where do you get coffee?” he barked. “I thought the last stocks of luxury imports went last New Year’s.”

“Try the cake. It’s not too sweet.”

Galt took a bite; it tasted good. He hadn’t realized how hungry he was; but then he hadn’t eaten in—how many hours?

“Like it?” Weinberg looked as expectant as a new bride serving her first meal.

“It’s fine, Dick. But—”

-

“A SMALL miracle, the man says,” Weinberg said, rubbing his hands together. “Come this way, Andy. I want to show you something.” The ecologist led the way through a long room where half a dozen green-smocked technicians worked over complicated constructions of glass tubing and containers of bubbling liquids. A sharp, burnt-toast odor filled the air. At the rear of the station Galt and Weinberg emerged on a sloping shelf of beach that led down to the waterline. Masses of dull brown scum lay in long windrows there. The surface of the sea was a dark brown, oily-looking, with sluggish swells.

“You remember the problem I reported I was having with the slime formation,” Weinberg said.

“I see it hasn’t improved any,” Galt said. “I hope it’s not interfering seriously with your work.”

“Fact is, Andy, I’ve about dropped everything to work on it. I think I’ve identified it as a mutated Fuligo Septica, probably introduced on some imperfectly sterilized glassware from Terra. We tried high-pressure steam first, but—”

“Just a minute, Dick. Dropped everything?” Galt’s voice was harsh. “Maybe I haven’t succeeded in making it clear that the mission of finding food supplements for the Colmarian diet is absolute top priority—”

Weinberg looked reproachfully at Galt. “Mr. Administrator, may I make my presentation?” His wide mouth quivered, the corners turning upward in spite of his obvious effort to hold them down.

“What the devil are you grinning at?”

“How did you like the coffee?”

“Drinkable,” Galt snapped. “What—”

“It’s made from the sporangia phase; the stalks, you understand, desiccated, ground, and roasted.”

“You made that coffee out of—this?” Galt prodded a mass of crusted brown flakes with his toe.

“Uh-huh. The cake was made from the spores, with an admixtured of Plasmodium, plus a sweetener.”

“Slime cake?” Galt said.

“Of course all this required a certain amount of processing. We’re running some ideas in glass, looking for shortcuts—for commercial quantity production, you understand. But with a little drying and compressing, we get what, unless I flunked Chem 1, is the best all-around livestock feed going.” He took from his pocket a hard, dull-shiny, purple-brown cake the size of a bar of soap. “Hence the goats,” he said. “And the chickens.”

Galt stood as if stricken. “But—if this is true—” He took a deep breath and became brisk. “Fine. One miracle to order—” His voice broke and he cackled in glee. “Dick, you sneaky bastard, you’ve just saved a world, damn your hide!”

“All in a day’s work, Mr. Administrator—” Weinberg, grinning, was gazing past Galt toward the open desert to the west. “Well, more visitors,” he said. “Word must have leaked out—”

-

GALT turned; a dust cloud was boiling toward them, raised by a speeding vehicle. The car swung past the station, slid to a halt near the storage sheds and was immediately veiled by the dust of its own passage.

“That looks like one of my maintenance carts,” Galt said. “What—” There was a shout. A man at the lab door was waving.

“Call for you, Mr. Administrator. Sounds urgent.”

Galt started toward the building, Weinberg behind him. Three men emerged from the dust cloud now blowing away from the car; they broke into a run on a course that would intercept Galt. Something bright flashed in the hand of the leader; the flat sound of a gun cut the air. Galt threw himself down. The man in the doorway started out; there was a second shot and the technician halted, turned, fell sideways. Galt looked up to see the second of the new arrivals knock the gunner’s arm aside as he fired a third time, the slug whining past Galt’s face.

—alive,” he heard. “We can always kill him later if it works out that way.”

Galt got to his feet. Weinberg went to the man who had been shot, squatted beside him, ignoring an angry command from the man with the gun. He looked up, his face pale and bleak.

“Pat’s dead,” he said to no one in particular.

The third man stood with his two fellows, all three looking dusty and windblown, a bit uncertain now. The wind whined restlessly.

“You, Galt, over here,” the gunner said. “You—” addressing Weinberg—” stay out of the way and you won’t get hurt.”

Galt walked over to the trio. “Proud of yourself, Jonas?”

Jonas swore and swung at Galt, knocked him down.

“Any guns inside?” Jonas called to Weinberg.

“No.”

“If you’re lying I’ll kill you. Get the stuff,” he, said to his companions. “I don’t want a stick left of this place to salvage.”

The two went to the car, brought out packages Galt recognized as standard melt charges. They hurried toward the entrance to the station, went past the corpse sprawled on the sand, disappeared inside. An instant later there were screams; steam boiled from the entrance. A man ran out, tatters of what looked like wet gauze flapping from his face. He stumbled and went down, lay thrashing. Galt, still on the ground, swung his legs, brought Jonas down on top of him. The younger man cursed and tried to bring the gun to bear; Galt caught his wrist, felt the superior strength of the other inexorably overcoming his resistance.

Suddenly Jonas was thrown clear. Weinberg stood over Galt, breathing hard. Jonas came to his knees and Weinberg swung his foot in a short, sharp kick that snapped the assassin’s head back. He sank down on his face in the sand.

Weinberg helped Galt to his feet; his knee was painfully wrenched. He picked up the gun dropped by Jonas. Men were coming out of the station, one still holding the live steam hose.

“There’s bad trouble back in the city,” one of the men told Galt. “It was Mr. Timmins on the box. He said you’d better get back right away.”

-

THE hour was near dusk when the copter dropper Galt directly on the grounds of Admin House, bypassing the noisy crowd surrounding the building. Timmins met him, looking grim.

“This isn’t just the usual unrest, Andy,” he said, “it’s a concerted uprising. Mobs at the port, the Power Complex—” he broke off. “What happened to you?”

“I’ve had a sample. A demolition team hit the Marine Experimental Station, killed Pat Rogan. Weinberg is holding our old acquaintance Jonas and a couple of others.”

Timmins swore with feeling. “They tried to fire the Comm Center about an hour ago. We saved it by the skin of our teeth. There are enough citizens on our side to make it a standoff so far; but killing a man—”

“Let’s get inside, Ben; I want a complete status report.”

Timmins finished his account twenty minutes later.

“That’s about it. The best estimate is three hundred activists, another ten thousand going along for the ride, ready to jump either way. That’s damn near half the population. Opposed to them, we’ve got a hundred organized militia with non-lethal weapons and maybe two thousand volunteers with axe-handles and chair legs.”

“Get some cots set up, Ben. It’s going to be a long night.”

“What do you plan to do, Andy?”

“Wait. Maybe by morning they’ll have cooled down enough to talk sense to. I have some news for them.” He outlined the gist of Weinberg’s discovery.

“But this is what we’ve been waiting for—even praying for at odd moments,” Timmins said, running his fingers through his thinning hair. “Good lord, Andy—this is the best news you could have brought—”

“But nobody out there’s listening tonight. Relax, Ben. So far we’re holding our own. Maybe this will tip it our way.”

All through the night there were reports of fires, quickly quenched, roaming bands of slogan-shouting looters, clashes between vigilantes and demonstrators which petered out indecisively. The hours passed. Galt dozed. Pale light was filtering through the windows when he was awakened by a man who burst into the office, without the formality of knocking. “They’ve fired the library,” he said. “A crowd of them got inside the kindergarten, too. Shall we try to hold it?”

“Let it go,” Timmins snapped. “We’ve got to concentrate on essential installations.” He broke off. “Sorry, Andy. It’s your decision, of course:”

“I agree. What are they really after, Ben What’s their prime target?”

“What do you think?” Timmins snapped. “Admin House. If they get in here—”

-

A MUFFLED explosion in the near distance punctuated the remark. Objects rattled on the desk. Somewhere there was a sound of breaking glass. Galt whirled to the window. Smoke was billowing from a point near the main gate, which was twisted off its mountings. Men came streaming through the opening in a ragged spearhead.

“Where are our, militiamen?” Timmins yelled and left the room at a run. Shouts sounded from the downstairs, accompanied by heavy thuddings. Galt arrived in the foyer to find a dozen volunteer defenders, all of them smoke-smudged and bleeding from small cuts and abrasions, grouped behind the massively barred doors.

“They’re starting to get rough,” one of the men called. “They’ve got guns—a dozen of them anyway. God only knows where they got them. Nobody killed yet far as I know, but that explosion they set off—”

The pounding at the heavy doors ceased abruptly. Voices could be heard beyond the heavy panels, shouting over the rumble of crowd noises.

“We’re in a hopeless position,” a man said. “We’ve done all we could—these hoodlums mean business. I say let’s get out while we can.”

“Dammit, you can’t run away now—” Timmins began.

“Go ahead, Jacobs,” Galt cut in. “Anybody who wants to leave now, make it fast. Thanks for your help.”

All but two of the volunteers departed hastily, some silently, some with apologies. A chant had started up outside the doors.

“What the devil are they shouting?” Timmins said.

“Give—us—Galt!” the chant came through clearly in a momentary lull in the background roar. “Give—us—Galt”

“The damned murderous swine,” Timmins cried. “Andy, you’ve got to get out. They want a scapegoat, somebody to blame—and you’re elected.”

Galt shook his head; he went up the stairs to the landing. From the narrow window there he could see the drama spread out before him: the ruined gate, the ragged crowd of rebels fanning out from it, forming a loose arc fifty feet from the steps; the packed mob beyond the walls, craning for a better look.

“Like ghouls, watching a beheading,” Timmins said beside him. “Don’t the damn fools know if these anarchists get inside it’s all over for Colmar?”

“Don’t blame them; they’re just ordinary citizens caught in something outside their scope. They’re waiting for leadership—any leadership.” Galt glanced at Timmins. “And if we can’t give it to them, somebody else will.” He “pointed to the tall man standing front and center, with a bandolier of cartridges slung over his shoulder, a heavy power rifle gripped in a brawny fist.

“A malcontent named Brauer,” Timmins said. “By God, if I had a gun—” He looked at Galt, dropped his eyes to the pistol in Galt’s belt. “Let me borrow that, Andy,” he said in a low, intense voice. “I can drop him with one shot.”

Galt shook his head. “You know better than that, Ben.”

“If killing one man will stop this—I say it’s justified.”

“I’d probably agree with you—if one killing would stop it. The fact is, we’d be giving them a martyr—shot from ambush. I think I know which way the crowd would go then.” He turned and went back down the stairs.

“Open it up,” he said to the two men waiting beside the big doors.

“Mr. Administrator, you can’t surrender to that mob,” one of the men blurted. “They’ll skin you alive. That’s all they want.”

“Who’s surrendering? Get that door open.”

-

OVER the protests of Timmins, men withdrew the locking bars, swung the portals wide. A sound went up from the crowd as Galt stepped out on the portico; it faded quickly as the big man named Brauer stepped forward. He stood for a moment, fingering the gun in his hands; then he turned and called over his shoulder:

“Let’s go; the rats are throwing in their hand.” He started forward, walking with a defiant swagger, all eyes on him. Those directly behind him followed; the crowd edged forward, sliding silently through the gate, spreading out. Brauer came on. When he was six feet away, Galt flipped back his jacket to expose the pistol thrust into his belt, dropped his hand to the butt. Brauer stopped dead. A number of expressions crossed his face; surprise, anger, determination. His eyes narrowed. The rifle in his hands started to come up.

“Throw that gun down or I’ll put a bullet between your eyes, Brauer,” Galt said quietly.

Brauer froze. He glanced at Galt’s face, at his chin, his belt buckle.

“You crazy, Galt? he asked “Get out of my way—”

“Five seconds,” Galt said.

“You want to get killed?” Brauer burst out.

“Four,” Galt said. “Three. Two—”

With an oath, Brauer threw down the gun. A murmur went up from the crowd. A man behind Brauer started forward.

“Get back in line,” Galt snapped. The man halted.

“Drop the bandolier, Brauer,” Galt ordered. Brauer complied. He looked up at Galt, his face slowly turning red.

“Come inside,” Galt said. “I want to talk to you.” The big man stood fast. “Move, I told you!” Galt snapped. Brauer attempted a cocky smile; it became a sickly grimace. He went up the steps. Galt followed him inside. When he glanced back from the door, the crowd was already melting away.

“You can’t get away with this,” Brauer was saying. “We don’t have to stand for this—”

“I think you will,” Galt said.

“We’ve got rights!” Brauer yelled. “The power belongs to the people!”

“That’s right,” Galt said. “I agree you’re under no obligation to support the government just because it’s there.”

“Well, then—” Brauer started.

“Certainly, you have a right to revolt,” Galt went on. “But that doesn’t mean I’m under any obligation to let you get away with it.”

-

“WHAT I can’t understand,” Timmins said an hour later, after the militia had reported all quiet in the city, “is why you let him get so close before you stopped him.”

“Simple,” Galt said. “I couldn’t hit the wide side of a warehouse with a pistol unless the muzzle was touching it.” He smiled. “Brauer made the same mistake in judgment Blum did—they both let me get too close. And when we started talking—I had the better argument. Brauer “agreed he would have made a lousy administrator.” He yawned. “Tomorrow we’ll announce Weinberg’s discovery—and a new plan for Colmar’s economy.”

The End